welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right ooh
Friday nights with Pat at the stoah yeah
so I'm Peter Lindbergh Stewart of the
stoah and this is a place where we go
here and dialogue about what matters
most at the nice edge of this moment and
today we have probably the baddest man
on the internet Pat Ryan and he's gonna
give a talk on drama drama which I'm ten
percent nervous about so what's gonna
happen is Pat's going to do uh share his
thoughts and then we're gonna look up to
Q&A if you have questions for Pat just
write in the chat box and then I'll meet
you and you can ask her the pact that
being said I hand it over to you my
friend hey folks thanks for round 2 and
thanks for bringing me back always
appreciated I'll do my previous format
where I explain what I'm gonna do and
then we'll just walk right through it
Peter and I had a great discovery
continues actually about certain topics
regarding how people are influenced and
how they're made suggestible is that
even true is hypnosis a thing are these
conspiracy theories true about how you
can make people a Manchurian Candidate
of course those are the contemporary
troops we have when we talk about such
concepts but what if it wasn't so
insidious what if you didn't need that
level of malicious intent to get those
type of results what if we were actually
doing that all the time anyways I just
didn't even know it so we kind of landed
on this concept called the trauma drama
where the stance that I'm gonna take is
that trauma is actually essential to the
brain this is a very complicated and
very controversial thing to say because
we all have varying spectrums of either
trauma abuse or terrible things have
happened to us this is in no way
designed to undermine or make light of
any
this is designed to explore the neural
evolution of how trauma even came to be
why we even have the capacity for it and
at the end there might be if I convey
this correctly I will display the last
slide without any words and we'll just
see what happens so much more I am ready
to begin
[Music]
okay so trauma trauma start as a little
monkey and end up an alcoholic that's
just how good so move on to the next
slide traumas start with the words right
but I'm not gonna defeat the idea that
trauma is is something that needs to be
redefined that it's too personal so I'm
gonna start in the personal way to start
at the personal is is a homo centric
concept called a definition so here we
start with where what it means it means
a wound to hurt actually its roots comes
from to rub or termed as in life like
irritate like to grab someone like do
this right that's an important
understanding if we're gonna cling to
the idea that trauma is this personal
experience so there's two highlights
because it implies that it's non-fatal
it's not wound to kill its wound to
irritate you that some of them and it
further just might being controlled hmm
so anyway because it's non-fatal and
it's personal it is automatically
implied to be homeless centric and
anthropogenic as a byproduct
so trauma is things that humans do to
humans and that's as far as the
conversation tends to go
get it from other spectrums or domains
because again it's it's incredibly
personal and intoxicatingly so so it's
very hard to you know remove yourself
from that kind of experience it's very
compelling when it comes to that so boy
that yellow line yellow anybody did that
can you please undo that Debbie yeah how
do people do that
there I think they're kindly
highlighting something okay I didn't
know what they could do that please stop
doing that I don't know if you can it's
just gonna be this yellow circle that's
into recording the whole time there's
nothing weird anybody's a pro a pro and
zoom that would be super but I'll keep
going until someone figures it out all
right so what I decided to do is
continue with the anthropogenic in-home
eccentric definition of trauma and we'll
start with a history of psychology which
is where trauma therapy even thank you
for moving that with it with a history
of this research even comes from and a
lot of these gonna be a little bit
academic but I'm gonna focus on what's
important about these things trauma
research comes from trying to defeat the
the Victorian British Menace of hysteria
in women that's where it actually starts
so the British Victorians were very keen
of their industrial accomplishments and
their imperial conquest of the lessers
and their hopes that they could
modernize them if these damn women just
wouldn't stop crying all the time and
that's as far as they looked at it
that was pretty premature to even come
to that conclusion
but they did it anyway of course they
were wildly wrong in their prescription
but this is where the concept of
studying trauma originates from at least
in the West and the modern West I should
say punctuate that so it starts from
trying to make very upset women less
upset not by dealing with their actual
issues of course but more like poking
and prodding them like subjects and
inefficiencies that unfortunately led to
which then leads us to it led to
premature categorisation of the problem
so the stereo was too wide of an
umbrella it didn't it wasn't descriptive
enough it was just stupid so you had two
different people is your name fraud
sorry did I say fraud I didn't say fraud
that was a bit fruity and slick no pun
intended but the there was two different
schools of thought he had disassociation
and he had double consciousness again
he's implied two totally different
things they imply that there's another
spirit within you right so this
association means you have multiple
spirits in you you can only pick one at
a time so I'm either going to be me or
I'm going to disassociate into some
other spirit double consciousness means
they operate in parallel and they're
influencing each other so these are
these are two high-level categorizations
of hysteria and that's what they settle
on they were there they're like a prop
they're like blind floating themselves
and trying to shoot a target
incrementing themselves towards
something more relevant so I'm not
trying to forgive I'm not trying to
create a basis in which we then you know
explain very poor conclusions that their
research has led to I'm just trying to
let you know where their brain was
anachronistically so we can make sense
of why we have so many misconceptions on
the concept of trauma this is again
compounding the the British Victorian
fixation on trying to make women more
compliant to the rapid changes of the
industrial period and it kind of led to
a bit of a backfire he was deciding this
he was basically stating that the
hysteria in women was was a byproduct of
fantasies of sexual abuse and know some
of these women were sexually abused now
just kidding they actually weren't
abused it was a bit of a problem it was
there was no experimental discipline or
rigor there was no peer review it was
just one guy running around saying hey
these things are happening I can just
bought into it cuz of slavery
and yeah it's just a mess daughter mess
this is not how you conduct these types
of research but but we all know that I'm
not really teaching anything new here
I'm skinny context so let's see this is
right so it was once again considered
that perhaps it wasn't just women doing
this we're men actually doing this too
and the answer for most of the research
was no that changed the world so with
the advent of fully industrialised
mechanical warfare in mass I think 20%
of Europeans male population died in the
four years of over one
concept of rolling artillery was
devastating people men would go onto the
front lines they would be exposed to the
horrors of industrial warfare whether it
was gas attacks consistent rolling
artillery barrage --is sniper fire
living in permanent panic trench foot
getting lice and mites sitting around in
the dirt infection although all the
forces of just horrors were inflicted on
everyone at the same time across
multiple countries for the French for
the British for the Germans for the for
the Slovak block as well
anybody who participated in that word it
was a full mobilized war so they threw
all of their males into it so in
addition to having these highly
industrialized nations their women going
and having hysterical breakdowns as a
byproduct of the reconfiguration of
family life in the reconfiguration of
industrial alignment now it was the
men's turn because they have all
experienced at the same time so limited
we're experiencing this initially now
was the men's turn they were dumped into
it because of the war so now they were
starting to do Express in mass and in
synchronistically in synchrony all of
the trauma that women were also showing
the same behaviour for and this
unfortunately had a had a very negative
side effect on the research of trauma
because this is it's just this is
terrible stuff because women were
associated with hysteria when men were
displaying the behaviors of hysteria
they were considered cowards because
they were activate women and so it
completely interfered with the ability
to research trauma which is again
another one of those first they missed
categorized the first era to abroad and
then they took an entire subset and they
missed categorized in cities pitched it
away just so they were given these two
massive sample sizes the early
researches and these didn't know to do
it did whether it was malice or
incompetence or a little bit of both
target that all day now men and women
are have finally displaying this kind of
thing this trauma this is unknown at the
time human behavior that we're going
through but was it Universal wasn't
all men and all women about different
cultures different cultures displayed
trauma in different manners
turns out the Irish were different about
it they didn't like showing pain
traditional North Americans were very
stoic about it they were like oh I'm
sick I should go to the doctor and then
I should diagnose myself as objectively
as possible leave my emotions out of it
so I can get the proper advice the
medical advice and then some of
Europeans stereotype of the loud Italian
so these every culture is very different
and how they express pain which gives a
clue about the trauma how trauma how can
you have this objective how can you
begin to apply an objective measure to
something that culture is so heavily
influencing stuff it's a really tough
question
let's see and then you get to
non-european Nations Nigerians Nigerians
for example it's a sensation of heat
writhing maggots it's not even like this
personal loss it's not like oh I went
through this thing in there no it's like
this thing is happening to me
it's not coming from me it's happening
to me that's a very different way of how
trauma is interpreted or looked at yet
to Middle East and especially when you
get that Turkey in Syria in Iraq then it
gets off the rails because there's their
cultures are old enough to have points
of reference about things that reach all
the way back into antiquity so as a
result to them there is no difference
between trauma as a mental pain and as a
physical pain to them is all physical so
when when this particular research was
done the people who were who were
demonstrating traumatic results like
PTSD or any type of psychological
compensation from an event of trauma
they were actually putting their bodies
in a state as if they were physically
ill so they would sit there like balled
up in a corner they they walk really
differently but they would convey to
they had this way of conveying to their
own peers that something was wrong with
them as opposed to you know stiff upper
lips so each culture had a different
strategy of expressing the finding and
ultimately experiencing trauma that bad
unfortunately goes against the narrative
of trauma being this big personal thing
it's my personal journey it's very
difficult to get the objectiveness of it
when you look at it from this level so
so far and again right here this is
another position that's basically
stating that trauma from Western
constructs and Western research as
individual in the focus but social and
political realities can be a root of it
but if you're looking at it from
individual sense like something's wrong
with me or something happened to me then
you're going to not look at the social
context that may be causally involved
whether it's the source event or the
route is there's another discussion
entirely but but those elements to
influence trauma type of expressing and
evolving to a person so this puts us in
a kind of a tough spot because trauma as
scientific psychology as a European
concept it's and that European concept
is kind of predominant especially when
it comes to things like psychiatry and
drug prescription and medication the
idea that all brands are the same and we
all have these people brains and we all
have equal cultures is it is actually
interfering with the research of trauma
and that's uncomfortable and hard to
have that conversation without it
turning into a blowout but I'm citing
what I can to mitigate that type of
thing so we've covered European men
European women different European
cultures and African culture Middle
Eastern cultures and it's pretty it's a
broad spectrum right there's a lot going
on in the human condition it turns out
and culture is playing a role in how
trauma is perceived experienced at the
fight so there's an instinct here
because we won't give up this got-damn
it we will never give this up we will
die by then we will wipe out the world
to make sure that scientific psychology
is true and goddammit we don't care what
the cost will be because fuck so when
you're approached with this question how
do we find a baseline how do we find a
baseline where is this mythical person
that is independent of culture how can
we identify this one being in which we
can then nullify or at least identify to
differential analysis on regarding
trauma and the answer is absolutely
fucking miserable use children
they had culture now children to acquire
culture fairly rapidly but not at all in
ages there's a gap between like zero and
two and three and this goes into a dark
place pretty fucking quick so I'll get
into this dark space and I promise I'll
immediately bounce out of it so you had
child sexual abuse that's a thing that's
also considered a post-traumatic stress
disorder just based on the expression of
behavior the child goes through it they
are displaying the same maladaptive
functioning as female rape survivors in
male combat veterans again going back to
that British Victorian challenge space
that they were trying to originally
applied Roma to so they had had to go
back to pre Freud and Freud and say okay
you're seeing the same behavior here
maybe children also get it too because
that children has control group pre
culture can act as that sort of way to
do the differential analysis between
other cultures so then you get into the
more detailed of detailed results what
children go through poor impulse control
aggressive difficulty with interpersonal
relationships you guys can read so the
research is done it has been done for
the past probably 70 years at this point
I would consider it a fairly dark
chapter in this type of research there's
still plenty of children who were
subjected to not only controlled
examples of these experiments but also
uncontrolled if you look at the way mass
media works which we will get there
eventually during this talk but they're
displaying children can't do display
PTSD when they are put under sustained
abuse now this implies that independent
of culture there is something about the
human brain that is that has either ways
to deal with stress or is reacting to
stress or or something unexplained right
so
let's get out of this dark place like
prison I don't like being here so let's
go find other baselines instead let's
take some presumptions before we get
there what if it isn't anthropogenic
what have we been wrong about this whole
time all of our research has been about
looking at how trauma affects people and
how people applied trauma to people and
it's all people-oriented but what if
what if nature fucks us up what if like
I don't know lightning bolt it's my
uncle it's pretty traumatic right and
didn't come from a person came from
floor or something so what if it isn't
home eccentric what if humans aren't the
only things going through trauma I think
that's a valid question
but if non-human mammals also go through
trauma like dogs or elephants that's a
fair assumption I think enough of us
have pets or worked in farms to seen
that
so let's either children alone for a
generation
scientists thanks let's go look at
animals right maybe it's their turn to
there's a lot of examples I'm gonna be
in and out of this one too because this
gets dark as well African elephants
demonstrate PTSD when they see their
herd get cult or killed in bulk they
have differences in how they interact
with the herds they then integrate with
their ability to follow age-related cues
gets completely shattered they
demonstrate depression as far as one can
do like putting their head against the
wall for example repeatedly banging
their head against the wall they will do
that so it turns out that social mammals
not just humans are also displaying
signs of trauma
again the question keeps coming back is
this fundamentally neurological is this
part of the the animal brain is this
like this person's brain is at this
cultures brain or is there something
fundamental to how the brain has been
organized in which trauma exists and
then there is another example which
there was another example regarding
animals involving a monkey which was the
saddest goddamn thing I've seen all week
and I decided not to put it in here but
I'll give you a baseline it was it was a
ten year study on a lab chimp who was
subjected to I think ten years of bio
weapons experimentation so putting
different viruses and diseases and
seeing that and it wasn't even trauma
from like it wasn't like smacking
someone it was putting that chimp into a
state where they're constantly in
disease for 10 years straight and even
then trauma happened so even if your
immune system was compromised in some
way from the jump you will still your
brain will still start to develop these
trauma responses and again it was it was
like 20 pages of the saddest shit you'll
ever read so I'm just not gonna put it
in here you don't take my word for it
but you can look it up ok so social
mammals are going through this - trauma
is happening here all right so we got
humans we got men women children
different cultures mammals ok that's a
lot but it's not enough reason it's not
enough is because
well but if it's not only for mammals
we're trying to answer where trauma
comes from so now we have to look
outside of mammals but if it's what
about animals who don't have complex
socialization elephants have it and dogs
have it cats have it we have it
what about things like I don't know ants
where it's just like genetic caste
system and the communication is just
pheromones what if this whole idea of
trauma being local and trauma being
personal what if it turns out that it's
actually universal and a byproduct of
biology that would be uncomfortable but
it would open up the answer these
questions so let's start using non metal
social animals and opens of our neural
trajectory at all so things that don't
have human capacity or social mammals or
things that are freaking alien like fish
right so even Petco says hey you fish
get traumatized get stressed out and
they demonstrate it right I didn't know
fish could get drama that demon Donna me
like I knew all the other stuff it's a
fish right but apparently fish get upset
they prescribed that the way to fix a
fish when they're upset is to fix their
environment surprisingly because they're
gonna tiny little cube of water and
their ph balance to be wrong or
nutrients could be wrong or whatever
anything could happen there so that code
has a pragmatic it's they didn't intend
for this to be part of this discussion
I'm sure but it's a pragmatic approach
to it's in it's an innocently pragmatic
approach to how to deal with stress for
something and there's there's a lot more
here if you decide to read into it the
idea of fixing the environment to fix
the fish as opposed to fixing the fish
which is what the individual
responsibilities of trauma dictates that
we should do so I found that to be
rather interesting yes you'd think ants
felt goofy trauma and you'd be wrong
so the way that there's a particular
group of ants Africa amount of delay I
don't know if I'm pronouncing that right
they have to go to war everyday with
termites around their colonies to get
food so they're there in invasive
carnivores from the jump that's just the
way the Geo destiny has set them out to
be and when they are wounded because of
these constant fighting they lose levels
many limbed creatures and they lose them
and when they lose the limb they spit
out some chemical substance and they're
all buddies say oh my god it's George
he's wounded let's go pick him up and
carry him back but it doesn't end there
there's some additional stuff about this
trauma response that's also interesting
once it's there they then proceeded to
do Medical prep on the ant now you'd
think these ants are breeding at a rate
that stupendous like 10,000 20,000 a why
even bother salvaging a single ant but
an Sapir to make the calculation that
that's a good idea we shouldn't just
told you shouldn't put the burden
exclusively on the Queen's ability to
create more ants we should salvage what
we can
and that's when we possible because of
trauma signaling so now we're starting
to see okay perhaps there's a function
to trauma as opposed to it being this
individual experience the Licking will
be done too and that this this
particular study was done in Switzerland
and Varion region of Germany so they the
Swiss have a ant colony that has one
feature that is unlike any other feature
it's an ant colony where multiple gene
lines of ants live simultaneously
usually they go to war and kill each
other but this one in the Alps they work
all together and they have the two times
like big big big big knives and there's
millions and millions of queens there's
millions of queens in that hive let
alone the tens and hundreds of millions
of ants and because of so much life
krahgg through it that these ant piles
generated stupendous amount of heat and
that in turn becomes a incubator for
bacteria and viruses so what these hands
have done is a they farm they form a
resin from local trees and then they
spit the formic acid on the resin
and then they take the combination and
then they clean each other with it and
it has antimicrobial properties so
they're actually administering anti
biotics to each other which is between
us and the ants that's the only animals
that actually do that to chemically
synthesize an anti biotic which is
fascinating but that's what's going on
here they're they're cleaning each other
to make sure that there's no infection
and this is disis ants whose brains are
so small I can't even recognize that
right so biology and neurology is a hell
of a thing and trauma appears to be an
important way to signal that whole
process but what about what if you're
severely maimed what if you're like
really mangled here whatever the trauma
is just unbelievably severe because the
call has to be made you can't rescue
every engine you don't have the
resources for it for starters so you got
a minute you gotta have a filter here if
you are severely wounded if the aunt who
is like three four limbs Dan's gonna be
a pain and it's flailing around and it
is sending the signal but the problem is
it's flailing around so much that its
buddies can't help it
you can't put a flailing an on your back
it's gonna fall off all the time and so
you have to make the call and say well
this ant isn't flowing as much I can
actually save this one and this one's
just do now that's interesting as well
because it's not like they're making a
moral decision it's not like they're
saying well I'm gonna save as many as I
can it's not utilitarianism it's all
locally there the grading of the caliber
that's being expressed from the trauma
the Pope battlefield is just immersed in
it after the conflict so it has to make
these gradient based decisions and then
it has to assess really quickly can I
even pick that thing up and it's not
making again it's not a utilitarian
moral choice at least I think so
interestingly enough one could extract
that this exchange could be the birth of
stoicism to a degree the idea that oh
well I'm wounded or I'm hurt or I'm
being traumatized by this thing that I
can't control and if I flail around
about it I'm not going to get the help I
want but if I'm kind of nonchalant about
it let it happen and sit and process it
that might be a way to attract the help
it's interesting I don't know if that's
true or not but it is an interesting
aside because ants already doing it
apparently but yeah they they flail
around it's basically a death sentence
so okay we got animals we have mammals
we got critters that aren't mammals get
in somewhere we're finally making some
damn sense here trauma is starting to
demonstrate functional purpose as
opposed to being this miserable thing
that happens to us and we're just doomed
to live with it forever there's actually
some neurological purpose here but if
it's natural it's been it's continued to
make some assumptions here
what if trauma is natural it's just
you're alive there's trauma that's the
game what if it's functional and it's
starting to demonstrate than it is I
mean what if it's required that's the
painful one that's a real tough one
the idea that trauma is required so
let's look into how that could be
and we'll use evolutionary psychology so
where does this even come from if we're
going to if we're going to make these
presumptions where is the driver for
this cognitive state coming from
predator and prey eating that's where
it's coming from you can confirm this
over and over again with studies like
this where you can take predator urine
spray it around mice and they'll lose
their shit they'll demonstrate PTSD just
by smelling the piss that's interesting
that shows that it's it's fundamental to
the neurology because this is their not
fundamental to neurology as much as its
it is this relationship between predator
and prey where trauma is originating
from and that's a that's an interesting
idea
because that implies that certain types
of trauma can be categorized a bit more
correctly as opposed to women nasteria
and men who have shell shock and child
sex survivors what if you get down to
that fundamental about how much of the
predator prey psychology aren't we still
carrying with us and we might be able to
identify how our stress response and our
trauma responses are formulating yeah
right so likely effects on fecundity and
survival are the norm in nature and so
the idea that it is beneficial for prey
to go through trauma because it enhances
their ability to survive against future
predator attacks so now we're getting to
the actual function behind it this
something can only exist if there's a
benefit a two-degree you can have some
maladaptive stuff as well but the
maladaptive is still functional at the
same time so how can that be
right that's a wild statement I'm gonna
delving deep in the controversy here if
we're still clinging to the idea of
traumas it's to personal experience so
just hang tight I promise it'll make
sense so this is the the predator odor
just just knowing the owner being aware
of it and kind of putting the prey in
that type of state and this is again
mapped at the brain level to there's
MRIs on all these animals that's showing
the brain is actually doing these things
okay so we've been I'm gonna I'm gonna
make a premature categorization here
feel free to trash it tell me I'm wrong
all day long I'm not gonna strongly
defend this categorization it's just to
drive a concept oh and maybe you'll see
some stuff and maybe you won't so what
we've been talking about and from what I
suspect most of the trauma that we're
describing that we go through
individually is actually prey drama
meaning we're describing trauma from the
perspective of being predated upon
that's only one half of the picture
because predators go through trauma two
it's just they go through it differently
so let's look at it Freight trauma these
are the four things that we associate
with PTSD according to some variant of
DSM that I don't even
so there's hyper arousal meaning when
you go through the trauma now all your
senses are fired up I'm now really
looking around right I'm smelling things
I'm tasting things I'm like alive more
hyper aroused and what does that do why
why would that be a response to trauma
well it enhances your alertness you just
got chased by a predator so you want to
be aware that if there are more
predators behind me have I really outrun
this thing you know you want to be you
want to take in and drink those details
as much as you can so you can make the
assessment that maybe okay maybe I can
start toning it down a bit maybe I can
maybe it's safe to chill for a second so
hyper arousal makes a ton of sense from
the functional trauma standpoint in
terms of the evolution of it unwanted
recurrent memories of the stress so
flashbacks right back in Nam and that
type of stuff but there's a there might
be a function to that too because if
you're forced to replay the experience
over and over again then you will be
forced to then extract additional
patterns and more associations from it
shit you might have missed when you were
too busy running so you're running you
know god this was behind me I'm not
really taking in all the things around
me I'm just jogging that tree I'm
jumping over that water I'm doing all
these things but maybe I missed
something maybe I was running and I saw
some ice and I was slipping around
and I now the lesson is when I'm running
from a predator avoid ice because that's
bad because it's gonna fuck me up so the
only way to get that retrained into your
brain is to have it forced into your
experience over and over again so now
there's a function to what is a
flashback so let's keep going
avoiding of associated appointments of
associative where now you have the
chance to practice what it is you're
formulating your mind or not you got
formulating in your mind you are
demonstrating
that you you are physically
demonstrating that you have learned
some things from the trauma encounter on
what you're doing is you're avoiding the
things you've associated so going back
to the ice example you're running your
supplies now what you're going to do is
avoid ice from here on out okay oh
that's predators and ice are a bad mix I
should avoid that so now you're avoiding
the things you're associating and so but
your your body is naturally it's
naturally concluding or I should say by
associating to predators
you are either enhancing your
survivability and the next encounter or
you're just batshit crazy you made a
wrong association that happens too it's
not like those an authority a referee
out here saying oh you're associative
czar correct you're just going to do the
best you can with the limited you know
meet space you have but you will be
avoiding those associative as part of
confirming that you have learned trauma
based learning and then social
detachment this one's a little tough I'm
gonna wing this one probably Bronk but I
think because in case anything that's
social by nature I realized the flaw of
using social mammals here I think
because they are social and there's a
lot of social stimuli going on all the
time that detaching from the social so
that you can spend more time with the
trauma and so you can extract all the
associative from it I think that's an
important part of making sure and
enhancing your survival for the next
encounter so you minimize your inputs as
much as you can and say okay let me
really process this and get what I want
so from the prey standpoint trauma is
actually really important for survival
if all of this holds have the details
and details and again I'm spitballing
here as much as I can but I'm assuming
that there is neurological functional
purpose behind the things we do and from
the perspective of tray prey it appears
that trauma helps them slough so we
catch my breath because that's so
predator trauma predators are doing the
same thing they have the same trauma
responses here
but there's a key difference for prey
the trauma is personal they do have to
learn these new tricks
to get better skillsets against future
predation so it's very individual but
predators their trauma is intrinsically
social
now why is that
so you'll see cases of monkeys
baboons and apes and although all that
family dogs
killer whales they're all having a
different context for the same trauma so
they're actually felting for different
lessons so for example there's there's a
pack there's a type of penguin I forget
which one it is
and monkeys do this too there's a type
of penguin I'm gonna focus on that
steals from other penguins so the
Penguins will get together and they'll
make a nest I'll take all the rocks and
I'll make their nests out of the rocks
now you can either go look for a rock
and then add it to your nester you can
steal the rock from other penguins but
when you steal rock from having penguins
you want to make sure that the other
penguins aren't around to see you do it
so there's deception and there's
deflection going on right so I'm trying
to hide the fact that I'm stealing from
this thing so I don't violate any social
resource sharing type of things that I'm
stuck in so that's a that's that's
trauma that's that is effectively a form
of trauma any psychologist will tell you
if you're engaging these type of
behaviors that's traumatic response and
animals giving us there are animals that
steal from each other all the time
they'll steal from other species too not
just from the tribe it only get caught
in the predator prey trap so they're
minimizing their exposure to the
clouding the analysis of the social
situation to you know maintain where
they've been plotting also happens this
happens all the time in males oh my god
alpha is there and the betas don't like
it they plot they form a pack and they
kill the often monkeys do this all the
time
humans do this all the time but that's
social trauma and that is predator
trauma it's needing so again
chimps I'm overlying on chimps here but
sometimes people get excited sometimes
animals of the packet exiled they failed
an attempt to take out the alpha for
example so they get booted out they'll
come back bleeding don't try for years
in some cases to come back pleading
that's that's predator trauma prey prey
doesn't really do that very much they
don't try to get back in the pack mostly
especially the case for rabbit their
life cycle look so faster
you're either dead or not but predators
are robust in terms of social
arrangements they have to work as a unit
and all of these trauma points are ways
to signal that something is wrong with
the unit something's wrong with the
group and so that's why again this is
now functional we're still in the realm
of functional improvement
except that in this case it's gone to
the social cohesion as opposed to an
individual betterment from the prey side
naked aggression is very common snapping
at people but what you're doing in that
naked aggression is you're demonstrating
your PAC utility saying I am still
fierce I am still useful in the hunt and
subservience it's very common trauma
we're like oh this person's beating me
fucking stop please I will I will
you know I'll respect the alpha and
self-criticism then that all predator is
the same there are there's there's the
the run and chase predator and then
there's the ambush predator big spiders
or some type of spiders so they dig
themselves in a hole in the know jump
out right they need to associate
themselves in their environment to see
if their camouflage works so if they
fail on a hunt that they fail to scoop
someone consistent one they're starving
they don't have food if expended a lot
of energy to go get that food and they
work so now they have to do like this
proto self-criticism have I have I
probably blended into my environment now
they're not doing this cognitively I
like the way I'm describing it but there
is the the trace foundation of a
self-criticism element is there so this
is there are there's overlap here or two
is not so cleanly separated there are
things there are trauma responses that
both predator and prey do like for
excessive grooming for example both of
these critters will do that whether it's
a cat or whether it's a guinea pig
excessive grooming is a common response
when social trauma is available but what
I'm trying to do is I'm trying to say
that there is at least
if we're going to accept that there that
trauma has a functional source and we're
going to accept that the primary driver
is the predator-prey relationship then
it's probably worth exploring how there
might be differences to them to then
make some proper diagnosis here so I'm
gonna go through a couple of examples
well first we'll just walk through and
summarize all the stuff I've been saying
it drives unlearning unconscious
learning so it's not like a lesson it's
not like reciting with a teacher and
saying oh yeah then you know on 1773
some guy did a thing it's more like
traumas there it happens so fast in a
predator-prey scenario that you don't
have time to actually sit and absorb all
of it you have to get the hell out of
the problem so you're running really
quick your prayed and so the only way to
drive lessons from that experience is
unconsciously the repetition of memories
avoiding associative to then practice
the things you're extracting social
detachment to enhance your extraction
abilities hyper arousal to to even see
if that if the predator is is still
there for the next count so this is all
unconscious things that your brain is
will do on your behalf without your
permission
and it's embedding it's not memorized
it's embedding into your nervous
response that's an important part too
and then when it's embedded it's not
recalled like oh I remember what I did
Tuesday it's replayed so if you go back
a couple slides you'll see that a lot of
the trauma people they don't actually
memorize the trauma but they replay it
all the same they go through what has
happened to them and that makes sense if
this is functionally true they're going
through it to extract additional
patterns so that they don't get
traumatized again right so you don't
recall it like you're reciting from a
test through replaying it because you're
still not comfortable with the idea that
you've taken all the lessons you need to
take from it and pray does this then the
replay memory adjust behavior that's
what avoidance social avoidance does and
the avoidance of associative so it's
adjusting how you're interacting onward
and that in turn is a that behavior
affects your fitness do you read do you
not breathe do you get do you help your
tribe you not help a tribe all of that
triples through it and of course that
Fitness is the driver of the trauma to
begin with the trauma relationship
between predator and prey around the
circle becomes a circling strife right
so here we are this is this fully
complete circle where the trauma is then
selecting for how to avoid the trauma
but then it's an arms race which is why
it's so difficult to dislodge so let's
give some examples of all this stuff
against pit bowling please tell me where
I'm wrong in this one I'll be happy to
do the research know this just give some
examples right so this critter shows up
it's hungry it's mad wants a piece of
that rabbit go but from the
predator-prey relationship the responses
will be different the rabbit this is an
irrational monster it's ruining its day
it has tend to take care of them this
damn thing wants to eat all of them this
is not what I signed up for I'm running
right the wolf on the other hand looks
at that and says as trash competition
I'll beat your ass you're nothing to me
so the the trauma response is different
between the two players a rabbit would
never come to a conclusion that I could
beat you I think it's going to eat his
family it has a history of eating its
family so the
and it drills we fundamentally different
between the two players see another
example grass how does prey look at
grass versus a predator like West prey
obviously sees food that's association
in this case and the preys the food food
so they both sort of seafood ones
indirect so one is very like to grass
put in mouth make Association the other
one is oh my food eats here so there's a
there's a layer of indirection that the
predator then has to make the
association of and it can do that
through predator trauma because if it
starves then it made the incorrect
Association of where the food food came
from
so then what if you start doing the
human thing where you start
experimenting with this type of natural
response and you start playing social
engineer or psychopath and you start
staggering the time and the distribution
of the replaying of embedded memories
can you modify Fitness and the answer is
of course you can so it's a rabbit a
rabbit be that a wolf a wolf so one half
if we take this group of rabbits show
them some wolves and some brass at the
same time what or the focus is separate
they're gonna say oh there's monsters
like no there's food that's a
disagreement here right so they do they
collectively make a choice for they
individually make a choice what do they
do they have options to pick from
there's no right or wrong answer the
context is very fluid in this moment
this wolf there's grass but he gonna do
meanwhile the wolf is doing the wolf
pack's is doing the same thing oh
intensive food here but oh no these
wolves I don't recognize their
competitors well things get sticky it's
not so cut and dry
this is bear natural selection does it
sting who's right who's wrong you don't
know until the body count starts
and then there's your fitness you've
modified your fitness because the
decisions that those individuals made
determines the fitness later on to spend
it in those mixed signals environments
then sometimes sometimes they'll switch
perspectives so this particular person
this particular entity used to be in the
wolf pack but maybe it screwed up maybe
made the wrong turn or interfered
somehow or pissed off the Alpha who
knows what happened but some severe
trauma happened at some point where when
the wolf looks at this grass and starts
taking on the properties of prey trauma
instead
it'll start being hyperarousal start
looking around you'll see this in zoo
animals they'll start doing all the
thing they'll start having prayed Romans
that have predator drama predator dramas
healthy for the predator of the social
adjustment and fine-tuning of a pack but
if wolf gets isolated it's gonna start
demonstrating prey trauma so then let's
look at a semi novel threats there's a
wolf classes there's the mustache cool
hat right so this is semi novel and the
fact that it's all wolf but there's like
slight modifications same thing you can
still modify the thickness here because
even if you hide the fact that this is a
wolf and you put these little cute
things on it the trauma that the
association's are still being made his
monsters here know they're fake monsters
that's not a real wolf it has a hat on
how can that possibly be a real wolf so
now again these this needs complex
decisions have to be made and they they
they are made in the natural selection
space wolf might see competitors the
other ones that's all fake competition
that's not real that's not relevant but
the natural selection still pans out
based on the decisions that are made
things might disappear there goes that
player too but then the severe trauma of
trying to make that decision might
switch one player to then start having
trauma of the other
this gonna happen it has been known to
happen you'll again you'll see this with
zoo animals who see this in
hyperaggression pray do demonstrate /
hyperaggression sometimes they
demonstrate predator trouble
rabbits are known to fight each other
constantly and not from mating reasons
either so the next slide I'm just gonna
walk you through it and I'm just gonna
show it I'm not gonna say a word
I'm just gonna see what happens so good
luck
you can affect the fitness of people
over a long amount of time
by trauma training one event as long as
it's common in semi novel you can make
people switch a trauma response to full
prey if you need to it's totally
possible that's it that's my wild
conjecture you know feel free to
criticize away I'm probably wrong on a
lot of the fundamentals but no wild
assaults on people's character at the
dark Stoa my friend so if you have a
question for Pat just write it in the
the chat box and I'll read it on your
behalf if you want me to or just unmute
yourself here's something
lots of stuff came up there but one
thing came up was your mention of
stoicism and sort of its potential
evolution and the thought of a virtue
came to mind being virtuous and I was
jamming with someone recently we're
talking about kind of like that and you
and I were talking about this to like
kind of the axiomatic principle or
foundation stoicism is being living in
accordance with nature or like our
friend Jordan Hall he says being right
relationship with reality and if you're
in right relationship with reality
you're in right relationship with
everything including the fight-or-flight
response and what comes to mind is being
virtuous as being in right relationship
with the fight-or-flight response so I
just wanted to throw that out there to
you and if you have any thoughts on that
or virtue itself
your mute thank you the argument I've
been making is that trauma is so
abundant and so abundantly present
across species that calling it trauma is
just as bad as calling it hysteria I
think in because of that the idea of
virtue and being in bright accordance I
don't want to nitpick on words come on
my brain wants to go there and that's
just that's poor virtual soothingly but
um but the idea of being right implies
information I don't have information to
make the right decision
individual has to make decision that
their local context is telling them and
the processes and the means in which
that decision-making and that sense
making dance is evaluating trauma does
have a role in that according to the
presentation that I'm trying to put out
there at least and the idea that am I in
a right relation with the moment am i
have I correctly assessed that I am no
longer being predated upon or have I
correctly assessed that I am being
predated upon validly those are those
are things that our brains are
constantly looking for in one manner or
another the the virtue
signalling sounds like social trauma to
me personally and I i'm using the word
trauma because that's the word view I
don't think trauma is a right word
person I don't think it's the right word
I'm just using it because that's the
part that's when someone is emitting
virtue of what they're doing it is if
it's emitting subservience to the alpha
you're saying I am I'm in accordance to
the packs efficiency so please don't
dislodge me from the resource access the
back gives me and so that's that's the
that's the hard rule like abysmal
science approach now if I step back and
I talk about the ideals you're talking
about from the perspective of the ideals
one thing that's not covered very well
in the predator-prey relationship is the
idea of self-sacrifice that's not really
abundantly well studied in case of like
ants and termites they have
self-destructive crazy chemicals and
just ruin any invader and so then you
got too close and then boom that you're
covered in acid that's gonna ruin your
life right so that's kind of a self
sacrifice but the idea of self sacrifice
is is it's almost like I don't know
whether it's a well-defined stoic ideal
or it's a virtue but I do know that when
you demonstrate it it can induce
traumatic response and all the world
watching but sometimes that traumatic
response can be good and sometimes it
could be whatever you're angling for I
can't give you a clear answer on this
one unfortunately and it does sound like
I'm trying to contrive this into the
pitch that I just made I recognize that
but I to get to ideals ideals are so far
down the line from the intrinsic
predator-prey formation of cognition so
I have to like walk through each and
every one of them before I can get to
them so that my deal space do you think
it's possible like you said the servant
asked
of the predator-prey dynamic do you
think it's possible to be subservient to
a higher ideal like the truth yes or
Jesus or whatever yes absolutely
absolutely because it's a little bit of
perception theory but because because of
the way that whether it's whether it's
learning in the formal sense or that
unconscious learning in which trauma is
heavily leveraging in either case you
have to make judgments from incomplete
positions and you have to be right how
do I know the perimeters not chasing me
I just can't like you know hey Google is
the predator still on my ass I can't do
that right so I have to make decisions
about my own life which only got one of
cuz I'm erratic running I only got one I
got an even decision that that thing's
not chasing anymore so I can help coupie
and stuff like that so neurology appears
to be selecting for means to make valid
decisions from incomplete spaces and
sometimes the artifact of that
incompletion can be represented very
cleanly in a belief or an ideal and once
it fits there then all of the traumatic
responses will interact with that I can
deal and believe as if it was as valid
as a reality concert so I think yes you
could you can have a predator-prey
relationship Trump you have a prey
trauma and predator relationship from a
predator trauma relationship with ideals
that happen to correspond with making
decisions from incomplete spaces so um
we're at the hour Margaret II or at the
hour you cool a stable of 15-20 minutes
filled with useful questions you know if
anyone has to leave you feel free to
leave but there's a lot of good
questions here so let's do Daniel if you
can kind of meet yourself and ask your
questions to Pat yeah I don't have the
option okay yeah let me
now you have the option to unmute
yourself Daniel okay
thanks Pat yeah I had a thought when you
when you map things out in the
predator-prey a dynamic in my mind it
could potentially a map to also a master
slave or sadist masochist dynamic and so
my mind went to this question maybe you
can riff on it what does your definition
of trauma say about sexual desire and
power dynamics and adult relationships
yes there is a lot of overlap there
because of the predator prey model to
answer this question I have to make a
presupposition that the trauma we are
experience that we are experiencing is
indicative of the structural limitations
of Neurology itself and what I mean by
that is that the reason we have the
trauma we have is because the way in
which the brain has to operate as an
efficient machine in terms of fuel and
resource input self consistent
management and then output into behavior
that then guarantees the brain can keep
going that's a that's a very complicated
dance and so in that dance that very
complicated dance you're going to come
up with a wide variety of different
behavioral outcomes and processes that
can then drive those many of your
outcomes in the event of the
predator-prey stuff that I'm talking
about that's just one subset mating
habits is totally driven by very similar
types of limitations and social habits
as well all of these drivers
intrinsically have to deal with the
physical space it's not just
abstractions to most animals the
universe is not an abstraction it's a
real and only thing it is a monad of all
that can possibly exist so you will have
overlaps of violence in the social and
the sexual space and depending upon the
neurological evolution of each creature
that's gonna manifest sometimes in
wild-ass ways for example there's
praying mantis eat your head you know
thinking humans has absurd but the
trauma is selecting for ways to minimize
its exposure because it's having an
effect on what is allowed to propagate
what didn't survive the predator you
know it's like this exception driven
duct-tape ball that trying to express
and any type of systemic way is just
kind of madness so it's just I'm
describing a fundamental mechanism of
the selection I couldn't tell you what
all the selections are with the
accumulation of it I can tell you what a
programming language is but I couldn't
tell you what every program is it's like
that so regarding regarding meeting
selection social interaction
predator-prey relationships I think
they're borrowing from each other's
toolkits
a lot there's going to be a lot of reuse
overlap as like a quick follow-up I
think the the piece I'm curious about is
it's also found in Stockholm Syndrome
like in in a dynamic where it seems like
an organism is going back to the
traumatic event or they've repurposed it
as sexual desire or something like that
which isn't necessarily the like not
everyone agrees with that premise but I
just thought it throw it in there yeah
it's feasible that during the replaying
of the trauma that the social and the
sexual contexts are also being trained
at the same time it's not just purely
the predator and prey the brain is very
limited space to to freely experiment
even with neuroplasticity it's not as if
the brain is turning you into a chair it
has it has to deal with very specific
inputs and outputs and your glucose and
your oxygen consumption is very tightly
monitored here so it has to play with
those within the bounds of that resource
so it makes sense to have
some sharing but like I said there is no
there's no referee on what associates
are valid and which ones parked that's
up for natural selection to figure out
that's that's that's a comfortable thing
for humans because we have this idea
that we can always make things better
but life is like it's hard sometimes and
not everyone wins I mean we're all gonna
die so we don't win right so that's it
but but I think you're gonna see because
of a resource constraints and the fact
that there isn't a referee of what
associate is a valid you're going to see
sharing these techniques
okay Irene would you like to unmute
yourself and ask about your question I
can I'll meet you there you go
hi hi everyone thank you so yeah I agree
that PSD symptoms and a lot of reactions
are a mechanism of self-protection to
survive in that hostile or terrible
environment but what about little
children that are pre verbal that have
attachment trauma where the parent is
there's not sexual trauma but the parent
abuse the parent is there then they're
absent they may have depression
themselves what about intergenerational
trauma so these are inherited responses
to traumas that you can't really
consciously process which is what's
happening with First Nations right now
how does that fit into your model so
because the predator trauma is
intrinsically social predators tend to
have this I'm saying tend I can't say
all they tend to have this feature where
they have to very carefully Medicare
their youth they can't just dump ten
thousand babies I'm just kind of like
yeah well y'all figure it out
the wolf has to very carefully take care
of its child we have to take care
probably not in case of what they lose
but but we have to take care of our
children elephants have to take care of
children monkeys of to take care of our
children
so the the predator trauma responds of
either failing to get prey or failing to
negotiate the resource distribution of
the tribe intrinsically leads to these
family formations for efficiency trauma
trauma response methodology in the
ecosystem tended towards so it does make
sense that if there is a familial bond
that is shattered in advance
disassociation excuse me and it is
allowed to persist that's where things
get too sticky that's where things get
real tough because in where you have a
lot of these tribal creatures if there
is a social bond that is a strumpet or a
social trauma a predator trauma has been
activated they will make it their prime
priority to solve that shit right
it won't sit there some of them might
sit there and linger debate isn't the
exile they do that lingering revenge
fantasy type of thing wolves do this
against the awful a lot but it can't be
buried forever
it does express itself so social traumas
lead to intergenerational trauma but
intergenerational trauma is only
feasible if the social trauma is allowed
to happen it's allowed to persist and
you can't resolve it which naturally
predators do they will resolve these
traumas and they won't let them sick and
let them invest and linger so I would
say that the concept of
intergenerational trauma is only
possible when you have so much resource
abundance that you don't care if
someone's traumatized because there's
more opportunity tomorrow do you have a
follow-up question to that because I
think there's different forms of trauma
so if it's like a freeze response you're
frozen out of your neocortex or you're
frozen out if you're a problem-solving
so that's how I see it so I'm not sure I
think you see it a little bit
differently than I do so I don't see it
I don't see that you learned that
quickly from trauma no it's not it's not
like it's not like you learn quickly
this isn't and this isn't like the
trauma file is on the hard drive and now
it's permanently there in the search
database it's this not it's not what I'm
saying
what I'm saying is that because of the
limitations of the brain its ability to
have things grafted into it to a point
that it's affecting your very
complicated behavior that takes time
that's why you need to do the social
distancing and that's why the replaying
is happening is because of the
limitations of having this really flow
through your entire being so that the
lesson is now part of your muscle memory
that takes time and every type of social
trauma that does manifest when it's a
person is going through it and then
signaling to others if the trauma is
there freezing for example that's
intrinsically social - it's the
individual going through it right that's
the mythology that all the trauma is
individual and nothing else matters but
the individual is demonstrating traumas
happy
to the tribe the tribe has to they make
a call do we deal with this now or do we
just say screw it there's infinite
resources we don't care about you and
that's so yes yes I would agree that the
idea of efficiencies in terms of speed
efficiency that's that's not what I'm
promoting at all so let's maybe do one
last question
devinder you had a question about
depression where are you Devinder when
on mute you there you go
devinder you're muted so you know so how
does a depressive disorder fitting to
the repeated trauma mother - so what
about depression that goes away you
learned for me bounce back but as he's
depression that never goes away say you
commit suicide or something like that
yeah so again the because there's no
referee of associative as a result it's
not as if you've made enough associative
and you can walk away I've made 20
associations about all the lessons I
learned from my trauma now I can walk it
off whoo I did it give me my medal um
there's no authority out there and say
that you found enough lessons and that
you're comfortable enough to actually
step back and engage that's gonna be up
to a combination of social factors in
biochemistry that is just a wild ass
dance you can engage in type of
therapeutical responses to mitigate that
to a degree whether that works not is
again that's it's more of a
probabilistic
hedge-fund approach as opposed to me you
know take this pill and you'll be fine
but the if my guess is that if we look
at the predator-prey thing as some type
of guidance again not the de facto
standard just as a method of guidance if
I am constantly trying to extract
additional associations from the trauma
then I know where I feel or I believe
that I'm not I am I have not learned all
of the things that have happened from
this and I am NOT in the space where I
can even continue until I go until I
keep going that sounds like a viable
outcome given how the brain is trying to
organize itself it may be compulsively
trying to extract associative and that
would be where I would look at for in
terms of like you know neurological
disorder if I had to put a drug
reference to something cool okay I'm
gonna stop there so before I make any
closing and that's what's bad do you
have any final thoughts to share on this
yeah like I said this is this is my
ongoing campaign to strike at all things
Western science because I think it just
needs to be done they've had a good run
I'm still there about a lot of the
things that they've decided and pushed
out of the rug so this is just and get
another expression of me thinking a
crack shat crack shot at that type of
direction so my bias is out there in the
open and obvious as a result of being
biased obviously I'm gonna make some
mistakes I'm going to make some wild
associations that shouldn't be made to
take that accordingly but I'm always
free for exception driven stuff I'm
always free for any type of
question or concern or criticism about
this hopefully this again I'm my goal
here is to say let's kind of back off
from trauma as the personal and let's
look at it in context as a functional
response from either why the individual
goes through it and then what that means
for social response to it I think if you
look at that systemically you start to
reorganize approaches to trauma
perhaps ideally in a more effective
manner very cool so we're gonna stop
there
I'll make some announcements in a moment
but Pat thanks so much for coming on
darhk's Toa Friday nights with Pat yeah
for upcoming events go to the store
that's CA next one is going to be
staying inside solitude from cultivating
interior life with Greg Sadler that's at
1:00 p.m. Eastern time and then
freestyling through a pandemic at 8:00
p.m. Eastern Time with Tyson Wagner and
so basically we're gonna do like this
freestyle rap uh-huh and with wisdom
obviously and Daniel you have a metagame
mastermind you want to meet yourself and
just talking about that briefly sure yes
we're prototyping how to create digital
gangs to help people develop sovereignty
and respond to the medic crisis so
tomorrow at 6 p.m. Eastern we're having
another session on that cool Thank You
Daniel and the story is based off a gift
economy I'm viewing it as a gift to the
world and this time of meat and if
there's any demonic inspiration bubbling
up to provide a gift to the stoa just
visit that website and there find out
more information there that being said
thanks everyone for coming out today I
Pat you cool to the stay on the line for
cool